This episode of Dissect is presented by
Amazon Prime. The holidays hit fast. One
moment you're planning, the next
everything's out of sync. Luckily, Prime
helps you catch the rhythm with fast,
free delivery that gets it there just in
time. [music] Prime's fast shipping is
always there for you during the
holidays, especially when it's last
minute and it just can't wait. Hosting
Essentials or the gift that hits the
right note, it's on Prime. Head to
amazon.com/prime
to shop now.
Let God Sort Him out by Clips is
Dissect's best rap album of 2025.
[music]
And to celebrate this near-perfect
project, I'm breaking down 10 of its
most impressive and complex lyrical
passages. Beginning with Push A's
opening four lines on So Be It
LV, I can show you how to bust a brick
if you let me. I'm [music]
like confetti.
>> Push begins spelling out Clips's name. C
L I P S E then adds ETP French for and P
as in the album's producer Fel using
French nods to the fact the song and
album was recorded at Louis Vuitton's
headquarters in France. But ETP is also
a homophone for EP Louis Vuitton's
signature EP leather used on jackets
currently designed under Fel's creative
direction. This leads into eightball LV.
Given the epy leather reference, Push
here is invoking the iconic eightball
leather jackets popular in early9s hip
hop. At the same time, eightball is
slaying for an eighth of an ounce of
cocaine. Setting up the next line, I can
show you how to bust a brick if you let
me. A brick is a kilo of cocaine, and
busting it down means breaking it into
smaller units like eightballs. I
monogram like confetti switches ready
continues both motifs and adds a third.
On one level, he's referencing Louis
Vuitton's famous monogram print
scattered like confetti. But monogram
also contains the word Graham, a smaller
measurement of cocaine that resembles
confetti when scattered. Finally,
switches ready adds the third layer as
switches turn Glocks into fully
automatic weapons, making the rapid fire
resemble confetti. This kind of elite
sustained word play is common place for
clips like when Malice weaves in movie
references throughout his standout verse
on track five Ace Trumpets. Over half a
mill we call [music] forasha reaching
for aasha never leaving home without my
peace like I'm a hot from the tribe of
Judah. I'm [music]
never turn the other cheek you'll lie at
the Oscars.
>> Malice raps over half a mill we call
ficasha reaching for aasha. Anything
above a half a million dollars is
considered bread, implying that anything
less is chump change. Accasha comes from
the Sanskrit word for sky. So Malice is
stretching his money sky high. In
Hinduism, Accasha is considered the
fifth element, an all-encompassing
medium that connects all things in the
universe. Malice plays on this Hindu
connection in the next line, never
leaving home without my peace like on
Mahatma. Mahatma Gandhi was a Hindu who
championed peace. But Malice's peace is
the opposite of Gandhi's. It's his p I E
CE, his firearm. The religious motif
continues from the tribe of Judah,
Amufasa. One of the 12 tribes of Israel,
the tribe of Judah is traditionally
symbolized by a lion. Hence Malice's
comparison to Mufasa, the lion king. In
Revelation, Jesus was named the lion of
Judah and Jesus preached non-violence
like Gandhi. Hence, we get the next
line, never turn the other cheek, you'll
die at the Oscars. Like his previous
piece on Tandra, Malice subverts Jesus's
famous teaching of peacefully turning
the other cheek while evoking Will
Smith's infamous slap across Chris
Rock's cheek at the Oscars. Malice is
saying if you were to harm him, he's not
turning the other cheek. He's going to
end you. And if that word play isn't
impressive enough on its own, notice how
Oscars contains the word Scar, Mufasa's
evil brother in The Lion King. This
movie motif then extends into the next
sequence.
[music and singing] Selling Lady Gaga
Hakuna Mata Island wearing tie-dye
umbrella in my rolls [music] match the
one that's in his mai.
>> Malice raps dressed in House of Gucci
made from selling Lady Gaga. Malice is
outfitted in Gucci which he can afford
from selling Lady Gaga slaying for
cocaine. But House of Gucci is also the
title of a 2021 film starring Lady Gaga.
The next line, Hakuna Matata Island
wearing tie-dye quotes the famous Lion
King song that means no worries. calling
back to the previous Mufasa and Scar
references. Tie-dyed shirts are
associated with peace, love, and a
carefree attitude. So, the image here is
Malice vacationing on a luxurious island
somewhere free of worries. This extends
into umbrella and my rolls match the one
that's in this Mai. A Mai is a cocktail
associated with tropical vacations and
garnished with a decorative umbrella,
which Malice compares to the customary
umbrellas that come standard in
Rolls-Royce luxury cars. Now for our
next selection, we're going to stay with
Ace Trumpets as Push A's verse is just
as impressive as Malice's white service.
[music] I am Luigi
and disappeared. I am Houdini. [music]
Look at them and him still waiting on
Yeezy. I hope you got your squeegee.
[music] Had your interviews. I just key.
Life's PG ASAP with Riri. You rappers
all beneath me. But love like the
beaches. International [music] flights.
Connect me to the Wii. The only way you
reach me. Huh?
>> Push wraps white glove service with the
brick I am Luigi. White glove service
refers to the careful handling of luxury
goods. Here applied to Push's
highquality bricks of cocaine. The
phrase also nods to the white latex
gloves used when handling those bricks.
In the Nintendo Mario Brothers games,
Luigi wears white gloves, smashes
bricks, and is Mario's younger brother,
just like Push is Malice's younger
brother. The next line, sold ecstasy and
disappeared. I am Houdini, continues the
layered references. Push sells drugs and
vanishes, keeping a low profile to avoid
arrests, a disappearing act he compares
to magician Harry Houdini. But this is
also a play on the 80s hip hop group
Houdini, who uncoincidentally had a
member named Ecstasy. Houdini's biggest
hit song was Friends, a track about the
struggle to find genuine relationships.
This sets up the next line. Look at him.
Him and him still waiting on Yeezy. I
hope you got your squeegeees. Once
friends and collaborators, Push and
Kanye West had a falling out here. Push
is calling Kanye washed up, telling the
stands still waiting on his return to
forum to have their squeegeees ready, a
play on soap suds and being washed. At
your interviews, I just Kiki describes
Push laughing at Kanye's recent public
insults towards him, most recently in
Yay's interview with DJ Academics. Kiki
is also the nickname of Yay's ex-wife,
Kim Kardashian. This marriage motif then
extends into the next line. Life's
peachy ASAP with Riri. You rappers all
beneath me. Push isn't stressing about
his fallout with Yay. His life is as
merry as ASAP Rocky and Rihanna's
relationship. Rihanna's global stature
and wealth overshadow rapper ASAP Rocky,
which Push plays with to frame himself
as being above his competition, saying,
"You rappers all beneath me, but loved
like the Beeges." Push gets love from
rappers like the popular 70s band the
Beeges who made many love songs and were
composed of brothers just like Push and
Malice. But BG is also an abbreviation
for Baby Gangster reinforcing the idea
that rappers are beneath push a season
OG. The final line international flights
connect me to the Weii, the only way you
reach me extends the motif. Push is
literally above others while flying high
on private jets overseas. Cleverly, Push
pronounces Weii the way many European
countries do, including France, where
the album was recorded, playing into
International Flights. Malice makes
similar claims of superiority in my next
selection, which comes off one of my
personal favorite songs on the album,
Mike Tyson, Blow to the Face. You [__]
are [music] screeners, we dream writers.
Took chains and touch change like king.
Imitation is [music] flattery. They seem
like us, but only 300 bricks can make
you Leonitis. My old plug as the new
plug to reunite us. [music] Declassing
my ears. Now let me see you bite it. She
want Mike Tyson blow to the face. I'm
talking [music] 96 ho with the base.
>> Malice raps you nwords as screenwriters.
We dream writers took chains and touch
change like King Midas. While his
competition fabricates fiction emulating
what they see in movies, Malice writes
from his lived experience. A true rags
to rich's story, a dream realized. In
this sense, he's King Midas, the figure
from Greek mythology who turned
everything he touched into gold. He
continues, "Only 300 bricks can make you
Leonitis." Leonitis was the Spartan king
who led 300 warriors against the Persian
army, which was dramatized in the 2006
film 300. Notice the motifs Malice is
developing here. King Midas and King
Leonitis are both Greek kings, while the
film 300 extends the screenwriter
reference. But the line also carries a
third layer. 300 bricks refers to
massive quantities of cocaine while
Leonitis doubles as a nod to Colombian
drug lord Leonitis Vargas known as the
king of kaketta like Midas and Leonitis.
Vargas too was a king. Malice then
continues declassing my ears now let me
see you bite it. Class Diamonds are the
rarest and purest something Malice's
imitators couldn't bite or copy because
of their expensive price tag. But ears
and biting also sets up the vers's final
lines. She want Mike Tyson blow to the
face. I'm talking 96 Hoveve with the
bass. Mike Tyson infamously bit the ear
of Evander Holyfield in 1997, just one
year after Jay-Z aka Hoveve dropped his
debut project, Reasonable Doubt, in 96.
Cleverly, both Blow and Bass in this
couplet serve as a cocaine double on
Tandra. Blow to the face is both a Mike
Tyson punch and a snort of coke with the
added layer being Tyson was a cocaine
user for much of his life. Meanwhile,
Hoveve with the bass is both Jay-Z's
bass heavy music as well as slaying for
crack cocaine, a nod to Jay's own past
as a drug dealer. Paying homage to
hip-hop legends is a consistent motif on
Let God sort him out. Like when Push A
shouts out Wuang's Ghost Face Killer on
track three, POV
Rolls-Royce [music]
like Sally's hair. The only Audi is
driven by my hair. Ghost face with
[music] the wrist bird falcon. Willie
falone trunk full of talum here. [music]
Shotgun with your ex feels like
Malcolm's near.
>> Push raps sand colored Rolls-Royce. We
like Saudis here. He's playing on the
fact that Saudi Arabia is 95% desert
sand. The same color as his tan
Rolls-Royce. Push wouldn't be caught in
anything less, especially not an Audi,
which is actually considered a luxury
car, just not as luxury as Rolls-Royce.
Hence, we get the line, "The only Audi
here is driven by my al pair." Meaning
that not only is he rich enough to have
an Alpair or full-time caregiver, but he
can also afford to give them an Audi, an
expensive car by most anyone's
standards. He continues, "Ghost Face
with the wrist bird falcon." Falconire
here is a triple on Tandra. First, the
entire line cites Ghostface Killer's
infamous golden eagle cuff, a gigantic
gold bracelet featuring a landing eagle
that sits on Ghost's wrist. A falconer
is someone who trains and hunts birds of
prey and push flips this to refer to the
slang use of bird which is a kilo of
coke. Falconire is also a play on
millionaire and ghost face with the
wrist is a reference to cooking crack.
So push is claiming to be a bird
falconire someone who's made millions
via drugs. The final layer continues the
previous Saudi Arabia reference as
falcons are a status symbol there and
incredibly popular among Saudi royalty.
The next line, Willie Falconee, trunk
full of talcum here, refers to Austo
Willie Falcon, a former drug kingpin
that operated one of the largest cocaine
trafficking organizations in South
Florida history. Talcum powder resembles
cocaine and is sometimes used as a
cutting agent. So push is obviously
referring to trunks full of coke. A
trunk also continues the vehicle motif
from Rolls-Royce and Audi, which then
continues with shotgun with your ex feel
like Malcolm's near. Push claims to have
your ex-girlfriend riding shotgun in his
Rolls-Royce, but the word play centers
around the famous 1964 photo of Malcolm
X holding a large gun looking out a
window. Hence, shotgun with your X. Now,
the Saudi Arabia motif in this passage
makes a perfect segue to my next
selection. At some point in this video,
I had to honor Farel's incredible
production on this project, and one of
the album's standout beats is built
around samples of a Saudi artist.
>> [music]
>> You ain't solid, ain't you? Ain't malice
[music] been quiet, ain't right.
>> So be it. Samples Saudi Arabian artist
Talal Mad and his 1979 song Maza Aulu. A
track Forel discovered when fellow
producer Swiss Beats posted it to his
Instagram. The majority of the sample
comes from this passage of the song.
[singing]
>> [singing]
>> So be its verses alternate between a
slowed and slightly chopped version of
this gnon flourish
and the vocal passage that follows it.
[singing]
Meanwhile, Soiet's chorus uses the riff
we heard at the beginning of the sampled
passage.
[music]
Clips and Farel originally had issues
clearing these samples. So, as some of
you might remember, the album version of
So Be It was changed to a sample free
instrumental on release day.
[music]
I could show you how to bust a break if
you [music] let me. I'm like confetti
ready. She leaning on a [music] stepping
catch.
>> We have Swiss Beats to thank for getting
the original sample cleared. When he
heard the alternate version of So Be It
on release day, he immediately called
Clips's manager to ask about the
clearance issue. As it just so happened,
Swiss was already on his way to Saudi
Arabia, where he has deep ties and runs
his own creative company. He promised
he'd handle it personally, and within a
half an hour, the sample was cleared and
the original, and in my opinion, much
better version of So Be It was restored.
Now, another one of my favorite beats on
Let God Sort Him The Out is Chains and
Whips, which also contains what I
believe is the best hook on the entire
album.
>> Sick
is just rich. Choke my neck, [music]
[__] and ice my [__] Beat the system
with chains and whips.
>> The chorus begins, "Uncle said nword,
you must be sick. All you talk about is
just getting rich." The uncle here is a
personification of America. Uncle Sam,
who criticizes the black American art
form hip hop as being one-dimensionally
obsessed with wealth. The irony of his
statement is obvious. America itself has
been obsessed with accumulating wealth
by any means necessary, including
centuries of enslaving kidnapped
Africans. The uncle's use of the n-word
alludes to this history, setting up the
central play of Push's response. Choke
my neck nword and ice my [__] Beat the
system with chains and whips. The entire
couplet is centered in subversion. Choke
my neck takes an illusion to lynching
and flips it into a diamond choker
necklace. Ice my [__] extends the motif
rather than the expected choke my [__]
Push adorns his partner in diamonds too.
Beat the system with chains and whips
sustains the subversion. Chains and
whips were torture devices once used on
the enslaved. Flipped here to reference
jewelry and cars. This same idea is
present in Push's use of the n-word as a
direct response to Uncle Sam using it as
a slur, symbolizing the way black
Americans have reclaimed ownership of a
word once used to inflict hurt, just
like the chains and whips. And so, where
Uncle Sam tried to paint Push's
obsession with wealth as a negative,
Push proves how black excellence and
wealth is actually a form of resistance,
a way to beat the system that's been set
up for black failure from the start.
Now, another standout hook on Let God
Sort The Him Out comes on the song FICO,
where Griselda Records artist stove God
cooks delivers one of the best features
on the album. You ain't [music] where I
go with a f you got a bag with one eye
closed. [music] My shooter turn out. I
heard the turn the crib inside out. Drop
the roof on you [__] Let the out
[music]
jacket boy
out.
Stove God sings, "You ain't been where I
go. With a fetty so strong, you got to
bag it with one eye closed." He's
saying, "The fetty or fentinol he's
bagging is so potent it'll make you
involuntarily wins." But fetty and eye
closed is a play on rapper Fetty [__]
who is missing one eye, so it looks like
he always has one eye closed. Fetty is
also currently serving prison time for
drug trafficking, including Fentinel.
The closing line of the hook is just as
clever. Fresh Prince jacket, boy, I cook
them till they inside out. Stove claims
to shoot his enemies so many times their
insides spill out, drawing on Will
Smith's character in Fresh Prince of
Bair, who famously wore his private
school suit jacket, Inside Out, to make
it more fashionable. Alongside its
chorus, FIGO delivers two of the album's
most virtuosic verses with both Push and
Malice rapping in the same complex two
bar double rhyme scheme.
>> I remember [music] late nights pissy
hallways driving me psycho. The money
[singing] wouldn't come fast enough. We
was back and forth [music] downream
moving weight was like light the rest of
y'all stuck in a rut [__]
>> All right, so let's break down this
rhyme scheme. Push begins. I remember
late nights pissy hallways driving me
psycho. The money wouldn't come fast
enough. Psycho and enough are the rhyme
words which get paid off in the
following couplet. We was back and forth
down streamline. Moving weight was like
lipo. The rest of y'all stuck in a rut.
Lipo here rhymes with a psycho while
enough rhymes with rut. The scheme is
notable not only for the two syllable
internal and two syllable external
rhymes but also for its unique
structure. The first bar of each couplet
is wordy and sprawling while the second
bar is sparse and punchy. That contrast
paired with the double rhyme scheme is
what gives this song such a unique
feeling. And both push and malice
sustain this same scheme for the
entirety of their respective verses.
[music] number like DMV. That was the
baseline. Check out register one.
[music] Miami [__] like big perm cuz
they numbers was phason.
>> Malice's adoption of the double rhyme
scheme centers on the two syllable
internal baseline and faison and the
external single syllable love and one.
He describes having to create a
transaction system like the DMV to meet
the demands for his product with
baseline being a clever way to describe
a long line of customers waiting to buy
his base or crack cocaine. He then
references the classic movie Friday
which features drug kingpin Big Perm
played by actor Faison Love. Miami
nwords like Big Perm cuz the numbers was
Faison plays on the fact that Faison is
heavy set meaning's drug connections in
Miami were moving heavy weight. This
leads into Cubans showed me nothing but
love. Malice implies his Miami connects
were Cuban who showed him love or gave
him a good deal. But love is also a play
on Faison's last name. Love, who
uncoincidentally is Cubaname. Cuban is
also a homophone for Cupid, the god of
love. And if that isn't enough word
play, Malice is very likely alluding to
AZ Faison here as well, a famous cocaine
dealer in the 80s who became the subject
of the 2002 film Paid in Full. Now, on
top of the elite word play and double
rhyme scheme, there's also another
incredible detail in Malice's FICOverse,
which has to do with all the numbers he
incorporates throughout it and what
happens when you add them all up. I
actually broke this down in a recent
episode called the most genius number
schemes in rap history, which I'd
recommend checking out if you're
interested in that breakdown and a ton
of other mind-blowing number bars. But
for the penultimate breakdown in this
episode, I want to highlight another
even more complex double rhyme scheme in
Malice's verse on so far ahead. [__]
[music] tried to sneeze at the blessing.
How could I just leave was the question.
Whistleblowers left me no choice. Ain't
no referees up in heaven. No mistaking
[music] me for the reverend usher in the
money. My confession how you pass a whip
a Rolls-Royce. That was me pre 911.
>> Let's use Malice's opening four bars to
lay out this scheme. He begins nwords
tried to sneeze at the blessing. How
could I just leave was the question. The
primary outer rhyme is firmly
established with bless and question. The
third bar pivots away from this as he
says whistleblowers left me no choice.
However, No Choice is being set up as a
secondary end rhyme, which isn't paid
off immediately. Instead, the fourth bar
returns to the primary end rhyme. Ain't
no referees up in heaven. Heaven here
rhymes with blessing and question. And
so we have four total lines with the
first, second, and fourth using a
primary rhyme and the third line using a
secondary rhyme. The next set of four
bars uses the same structure. The first
two bars continue the primary heaven
rhyme. No mistaking me for the reverend
ushering the money my confession. The
third line, how your pastor whip a
Rolls-Royce, finally pays off the
secondary rhyme as Rolls-Royce rhymes
with the previous No Choice. The fourth
bar then returns to the primary heaven
rhyme, That Was Me Pre 911. It's an
incredibly impressive scheme that
sustains the entire verse, and despite
the structural complexity, Malice
doesn't sacrifice his word play. For
instance, no mistaking me for the
reverend ushering the money, my
confession. In his personal genius
annotation, Malice confirmed this as a
triple on tandra. The central meaning is
that Malice, despite being a devout man
of God, isn't overly pious like a
reverend and still appreciates ushering
in pockets full of money. A church usher
is also the one who collects the weekly
cash offerings from the congregation.
Finally, the line is a play on the R&B
artist Usher and his most popular album,
Confessions. Now, for our 10th and final
selection, I want to switch things up a
little because as much as I love Kips's
luxury coke raps, part of what makes God
Sort Them Out so special is the maturity
and perspective both Push and Malice
exhibit throughout the project. This is
most evident on the opening track, Birds
Don't Sing. Known historically for using
birds as slang for Kilos of Cocaine, the
duo subverts expectations by turning the
phrase into a heartfelt tribute to their
mother and father, who passed away just
4 months apart. Push's verse focuses on
their mother while Malice's centers
their father including these incredibly
moving final four lines.
>> Don't [music] sing if the words don't
sting. Your last few words in my ears
still ring. You told me that you love
me. It was all in your tone. I love my
two sons to your phone. Now you [music]
>> Malice recounts that the last words he
heard from his father were I love you.
Then after his father's death, he
discovered that all of his father's
online passwords were, "I love my two
sons." It's a profoundly intimate detail
that shows that his father's love was
embedded into every facet of his life.
For Malice, discovering this had to be
deeply moving, a reminder that his
father carried that love and devotion
with him everywhere, even in spaces no
one else was meant to see. Touching
moments like this reminds us why clips
stand apart as writers. Unlike God sort
them out, they can prove they can do
more than craft clever bars about drugs
and luxury. They can also deliver
passages that are deeply personal and
profoundly human. That range from
cocaine on tandras to moving reflections
on family and loss is what makes Clips
not just great rappers, but [music]
great writers. And it's also why Let God
Sort them Out is Dissects 2025 rap album
of the year.
[music]
>> [music]
>> This episode is brought to you by Amazon
Prime. The holidays move fast, so stay
in sync with Prime's fast, free
delivery. Admittedly, I sometimes wait
till the last minute to buy my gifts,
and I've been saved by Prime more than a
few times. That's because Prime's fast
shipping is always there for you during
the holidays, especially when it's last
minute and can't wait. Need that final
gift or holiday essential in a flash?
It's on Prime. Head to amazon.com/prime
to shop now.